Okay fine. Okay good. So today is פא Pe Aleph and we
start at the משנה Mishna and let's give it a look. So
we've been dealing with the whole idea of a סריס Saris and
does a we sort of have moved back and forth between issues
about the actual איסורים Issurim of getting married סריס Saris and a
ממזר Mamzer etc. to the issues about חליצה Chalitzah and יבום Yibum
getting back to those. And we dealt with ספק Safek that a
סריס Saris even though cannot have kids can do יבום Yibum if
he's a ספק Safek of a סריס. Saris. If he's a סריס
חמה Saris Chama according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because he's somehow
not categorically excluded even though I'm sorry, I take that back if
he's a סריס אדם Saris Adam because he was able to at
one stage in his life do it. A סריס חמה Saris Chama
cannot. And now we pick up at the next משנה. Mishna. סריס
חמה Saris Chama so a סריס חמה Saris Chama that again according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which we're assuming is the סתם Stam
here cannot do יבום Yibum and
חליצה. Chalitzah. So כהן שנשא בת ישראל Kohen shenasa Bat Yisrael now
you had a כהן Kohen who is a סריס חמה Saris Chama
who married a Jewish woman meaning a non-בת כהן Bat Kohen מאכילה
בתרומה Maachilah biTrumah he can
she can still eat תרומה Trumah on his behalf. Now it's only
if he's a סריס חמה. Saris Chama. If he's a סריס אדם
Saris Adam then he's a פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka, then the marriage
is forbidden and then she becomes a חללה Chalalah as a result.
But if he's a סריס חמה Saris Chama although he cannot have
kids, there's no איסור Issur being done and she can eat תרומה
Trumah because she's married to him. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים אנדרוגינוס
כהן שנשא בת ישראל Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon omrim Androgynos Kohen shenasa
Bat Yisrael and now we shift I mean now you understand why
once you get through all of the צרת ערוה, Tzarat Ervah, you
know יבמות Yevamos is such like a rich מסכת. Masechet. I mean
you know, you're dealing with all these things ממזר, Mamzer, סריס Saris
etc. and now we get to a discussion about the status of
an אנדרוגינוס. Androgynos. So somebody who's an androgen androgynous androgen would be
the noun, right? Anyway, is there a noun androgen? Right here. It's
okay. Anyway, somebody who's
androgynous who has both male and female genitalia. What is his halachic
status? So the normal thing to think is that he would be
a ספק. Safek. Do you categorize him as a male or a
female? There are actually two other possibilities other than ספק. Safek. Any
any idea what those other two possibilities are?
Male or female. No, one is both.
בריה בפני עצמו. Berya bifnei atzmo. He's just there's a third category
as they say. It's very interesting, not in the whole transgender transsexual
issues but in another whole sort of issue the intersexual sort of
issue which is, you know, dividing the world in binarily into male
and female or do you accept the idea that there could be
some something that is neither male nor female some intersex. So הלכה
Halacha actually recognizes that possibility with an and with an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos
that it's neither male nor female, some some other category. And the
third possibility is what do you think? One is ספק, Safek, one
is בריה בפני עצמו. Berya bifnei atzmo.
Well,
it's ודאי Vaday but which one do you think it would be
ודאי?
Vaday? Female.
So the third possibility is מצד החומרות. M'tzad hachumrot. Why? Because it
comes from a certain type of a perspective, one might say a
male perspective, that being male is having male male genitalia and female
is the not different genitalia but the absence of male genitalia. So
therefore somebody that is both male and female because he has male
genitalia is a male.
Sort of like a Christian approach?
Well, what can I tell you. So that is the third approach.
It reminds me of a statement that Elliot Wolfson said about the
Kabbalistic idea of God. You know the Kabbalistic idea of God is
that you have, you know, one side is all the male sides
of the ספירות Sefirot and one is all the female sides of
the ספירות. Sefirot. Okay, but what's like God's gender according to this?
So he said according to the קבלה, Kabbalah, God is a male
androgynous.
So he's got male and female characteristics but bottom line God's a
male. So anyway,
alright, so
אנדרוגינוס. Androgynos. So that's the three possibilities for an אנדרוגינוס. Androgynos. So
רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים אנדרוגינוס כהן שנשא בת ישראל
Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi
Shimon omrim Androgynos Kohen shenasa Bat Yisrael if you have an androgynous
כהן Kohen who marries a Jewish woman, so מאכילה בתרומה Maachilah biTrumah
can make her eat תרומה, Trumah, which means that presumably an אנדרוגינוס
Androgynos according to him is what of the three possibilities I just
gave you? If the woman he's married to can eat תרומה? Trumah?
He's a man.
He's a male! He has to to marry a woman he's got
to be male. If he was a ספק Safek or if he
was a בריה בפני עצמו Berya bifnei atzmo presumably this woman would
not halachically be married to him, certainly not
ודאי.
Vaday. Is there any difference halachically between a male and an אנדרוגינוס?
Androgynos?
Probably but okay that's a good question. רבי יהודה אומר טומטום שנקרא
ונמצא זכר Rabbi Yehuda omer Tumtum shenikra venimtza zachar a טומטום Tumtum
is somebody whose genitalia were covered up and then at a certain
point of his life the the skin covering tore and you see...
saw that he was actually had was a male, he had male
genitalia. לא יחלוץ lo yachlotz מפני שהוא כסריס. mipnei she-hu ke-sariss. If
he's one of the brothers, he cannot do חליצה chalitzah because he
is like a סריס. sariss. One wonders what the כ kaf is,
but basically but let's assume it means he is a סריס, sariss,
that somebody who is born with that condition, the assumption is is
that he will not be able to have children and this was
a סריס חמה, sariss chama, it was a condition from the time
of birth, and therefore he is excluded from
חליצה. chalitzah. אנדרוגינוס נושא אבל לא נישא. androgynos nosei aval lo nissa.
Now continuing with the idea that we heard from רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, an אנדרוגינוס androgynos can marry a
woman but he cannot be married by a man, again assuming that
he is a male. Okay.
רבי אליעזר אומר אנדרוגינוס חייבים עליו סקילה כזכר. Rabbi Eliezer omer androgynos
chayavim alav sekilah ke-zachar. If an אנדרוגינוס androgynos marries a man, then
actually it would be considered an act of homosexuality. So seems to
be that the last positions are that he is a male and
therefore he can marry a woman but not be married, whether what
exactly is the debate between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the תנא
קמא, Tanna Kamma, is there a debate? Is it possible that one
of these positions works with the idea of ספק? safek? That is
not clear. We will see all of this fun stuff in the
גמרא, Gemara, not when I'm here. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara we're going to look at while I'm here.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, פשיטא, peshita, obviously if an
אנדרוגינוס androgynos is, excuse me, obviously a סריס חמה, sariss chama, his
wife can eat תרומה. terumah. If he's a כהן, kohen, he's not
a פצוע דכא, patsua daka, it was a natural condition and therefore
why should his wife not be able to eat
תרומה? terumah? מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might have thought מוליד מאכיל
ושאינו מוליד אינו מאכיל, molid ma'achil veshe'eino molid eino ma'achil, only one
who can have kids can have his wife eat, because it says
יליד ביתו הם יאכלו בלחמו, yelid beito hem yochlu belachmo, so maybe
it's only somehow in the context of a marriage that would lead
to procreation or whatever to lead to progeny, קמשמע לן ka mashma
lan that we don't say that, she's his wife and she's not
פסולה, pesulah, so she can eat תרומה. terumah. Yeah. Yes.
Why should there, I'm
listening, yeah go ahead.
Why should why is there a difference between a סריס חמה sariss
chama and a טומטום שנקרע? tumtum she-nikra?
There is not a difference. Who said there was a difference?
Well,
let's see. The סריס חמה sariss chama מאכיל בתרומה? ma'achil bi-terumah? Yeah.
And the טומטום שנקרע לא יחלוץ. tumtum she-nikra lo yachlotz. Right. So
they're both not being treated as a male whereas, no
in both cases he's a male that can't that can't have kids.
So in the first part of the משנה Mishnah it was only
telling you a הלכה halacha about תרומה terumah and then it told
you a הלכה halacha about חליצה, chalitzah, but they're both true.
There isn't a difference.
There isn't a difference. I mean why it was framed one in
a נקרא nikra and the other in a case of סריס sariss
is I don't know, but it's the same הלכה. halacha.
But this הוה אמינא hava amina there would also apply to an
old כהן? kohen?
Yeah, oh I don't know, presumably not, presumably it meant somebody who's
actual physical condition made it impossible, that's the whole idea of a
סריס sariss that somehow his personal status, it's not just that he's
an עקר, akar, he's a סריס, sariss, so that's a more reason
to categorically frame him differently, okay, which is why for example an
עקר akar does חליצה chalitzah but a סריס, sariss, you know, does
not and so on.
Okay, so that makes it the difference between the הלכות halachot of
חליצה chalitzah and the הלכות halachot of תרומה. terumah.
So a סריס חמה, sariss chama, let me make it simple, a
סריס חמה sariss chama can feed his wife can eat תרומה terumah
but he doesn't do חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. And a טומטום שנקרע tumtum
she-nikra is in the category of a סריס חמה. sariss chama. Right.
It's just confusing because it gave a different הלכה halacha for the
different scenario.
But I get, but in other words is the criterion is there
must be criteria other than maleness, right, to make a distinction between
those two? You have to be male to give תרומה terumah to
be able to give תרומה. terumah. Yes. You have to be male
to be able to do the חליצה. chalitzah.
Yes. But the exclusion from חליצה chalitzah is as we saw before
because if you weren't if you were never in the category of
having kids because you were born with this condition, then you're excluded
from the whole idea of ייבום yibbum and חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, it
fits. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון
אומרים אנדרוגינוס. Rabbi Yose ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim androgynos. And now we get
to the אנדרוגינוס androgynos who is married to a בת ישראל, bat
Yisrael, she can eat תרומה, terumah, which assumes that an אנדרוגינוס androgynos
is הלכתית halachit a male. So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
מאכילה בתרומה ואין מאכילה בחזה ושוק. ma'achila bi-terumah ve-ein ma'achila be-chazeh ve-shok.
Yes, she can eat תרומה, terumah, but she cannot eat what? What?
But she cannot eat קדשים. kodashim. Right, if the כהן's kohen wife
eats קדשים. kodashim. רבי יוחנן אמר אף מאכילה בחזה ושוק. Rabbi Yochanan
amar af ma'achila be-chazeh ve-shok.
No, she can even eat the קדשים kodashim that a כהן's kohen
wife is entitled to eat. ולריש לקיש אישמיע לן חזה ושוק דאורייתא.
U-le-Reish Lakish ishmi'a lan chazeh ve-shok d'oraita.
So according, now presumably the גמרא's Gemara going to assume that if
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't want her to eat חזה ושוק, chazeh
ve-shok, he is doubt, he he's he doesn't feel that she's complete
necessarily married to this אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. So the position that ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish is coming from the position that an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is
a ספק, safek, not definitely a male. And if it's a ספק,
safek, she can't eat חזה ושוק chazeh ve-shok because she might not
be married to him, he might be a she, okay, and therefore
can't eat חזה ושוק. chazeh ve-shok. So then the question is so
then why eat תרומה? terumah? So the גמרא's Gemara going to basically
say תרומה terumah would be a case where it would be rabbinic,
חזה ושוק chazeh ve-shok is never rabbinic, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
is saying that this אנדרוגינוס androgynos is a ספק, safek, this woman
is only doubtfully married to him, it depends on whether he's considered
a male or not, so therefore that is enough to allow her
to eat תרומה. terumah. תרומה Trumah at- which is rabbinic nowadays, but
not to- would be nowadays תרומה Trumah is rabbinic and not חזה
ושוק. Hazeh va-shok. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan on the other hand holds
like the simple read of the משנה Mishna that androgynous is definitely
a male and therefore a woman married to an androgynous כהן Kohen
is completely married to a male כהן Kohen and can eat תרומה
Trumah and can eat חזה ושוק Hazeh va-shok no different. So let's
take a look. ולריש לקיש מאי תנא חזה ושוק דאורייתא, U'Leish Lakish
mai tana Hazeh va-shok d'oraisa, why does he say that she cannot
eat the, you know, breast and the side of the קדשים Kodshim
that a כהן Kohen and his family eat of שלמים Shlamim because
it's biblical and therefore this is like a ספק safek case. So
תרומה נמי דאורייתא? Trumah nami d'oraisa? תרומה Trumah is also biblical. גמרא
Gemara says, no. הכא במאי עסקינן בתרומה בזמן הזה דרבנן. Hacha b'mai
askinan b'Trumah bizman hazeh derabbanan. We're talking about תרומה Trumah nowadays which
is rabbinic, presumably with the assumption that after the destruction of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash the land lost its sanctity for purposes of
תרומה Trumah and מעשרות, Ma'asros, which is a major debate, there could
be other reasons why תרומה Trumah nowadays is rabbinic but let's go
with that one and therefore it's after the חורבן Churban and after
the destruction and תרומה Trumah is only rabbinic and therefore he's lenient
for תרומה Trumah but not for חזה ושוק. Hazeh va-shok.
Wait we don't give it to a כהן Kohen these days right?
We just let it sort of just deteriorate?
Yeah but that has to do with the fact that we're all
טמאים tamei and stuff. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אבל בזמן שבית המקדש קיים מאי? aval bizman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam mai?
But what would you say? Okay fine the גמרא Gemara says, so
that's your difference, rabbinic or biblical. So what would you say in
the time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash when תרומה Trumah itself
would be biblical? מאי לאו שלא תאכל תרומה? Mai? Lav she-lo tachal
Trumah? Because it would be- because then it would be biblical. So
if that's true the difference is not between חזה ושוק Hazeh va-shok
as opposed to תרומה. Trumah. The question is תרומה Trumah nowadays as
opposed to when תרומה Trumah was biblical. עד דתני אימא אכילה בחזה
ושוק, Ad d'tani eima achila b'Hazeh va-shok, if you're saying that she
cannot eat, he cannot feed her, have her eat on his behalf
the breast and the side, לפלוג ולתני בדידיה. liflog v'lisni b'didi. Make
a distinction within תרומה Trumah itself. במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim,
when can she eat? בתרומה דרבנן, b'Trumah derabbanan, rabbinic תרומה Trumah nowadays,
אבל בתרומה דאורייתא, aval b'Trumah d'oraisa,
in biblical תרומה, Trumah, so לא. lo.
And anyway you can't say, and the scenario of חזה ושוק Hazeh
va-shok is when they're in a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So if
you're anyway going to contrast it to a time when there's a
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, why run to חזה ושוק Hazeh va-shok to
the קדשים? Kodshim? Just talk about תרומה Trumah itself when there's a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי נמי קאמר.
hachi nami ka-amar. Yeah that is what he's saying. כשהוא מאכילה Keshu
hu ma'achila
when he is having her eat on his behalf, מאכילה בתרומה בזמן
הזה דרבנן. ma'achila b'Trumah bizman hazeh derabbanan. It's rabbinic תרומה Trumah nowadays
which is rabbinic. ואין מאכילה V'ein ma'achila and he doesn't have her
eat on his behalf בזמן חזה ושוק, bizman Hazeh va-shok,
at the time- very weak answer- at the time when you would
be bringing קדשים. Kodshim. So in the context where she would eat
קדשים, Kodshim, like at the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
not only does she not eat קדשים, Kodshim, but אפילו בתרומה דרבנן
afilu b'Trumah derabbanan in that time, and now it's a- now we're
adding a חידוש chiddush that you wouldn't have anticipated, at the time
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash she won't even eat rabbinic תרומה.
Trumah. Now what rabbinic תרומה Trumah is there at the time of
the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So it's תרומה א-, trumah-at, תרומה Trumah
on fruit. Okay, רש"י Rashi continuously says, this is a bit of
a דעה יחידאה, deiya yechidana, but it's generally consensus that biblical תרומה
Trumah is only what it says in the תורה. Torah. It says
תרומה Trumah by דגן תירוש ויצהר. dagan tirosh v'yitzhar. Grains, the five
grains, תירוש tirosh which is wine and יצהר yitzhar which is oil.
Anything else, תרומה Trumah of fruit is rabbinic even at the time
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So now we're adding like a
little חידוש. chiddush. At the time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
she can't eat תרומה. Trumah. Not only can she not eat biblical
תרומה Trumah but then she couldn't eat even rabbinic תרומה. Trumah. Because
since it's a period of biblical תרומה, Trumah, we're going to be
strict across the board. דילמא אתי למיכל בתרומה דאורייתא, Dilma asi l'ochla
b'Trumah d'oraisa,
since it's possible at that time in history that somebody would come
about to eat biblical תרומה, Trumah, when there is biblical תרומה Trumah
that exists, we're going to be strict across the board. So bottom
line is we have a little bit of a חידוש chiddush that
he would even apply it to rabbinic תרומה Trumah at a time
of biblical תרומה. Trumah. But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying, I
consider this androgynous a ספק, safek, this woman is only married to
him מספק misafek because he might be a man, he might be
a woman, and therefore she can eat rabbinic תרומה Trumah at a
time when no biblical תרומה Trumah exists and there's no possibility of
any דאורייתא d'oraisa problem. But at a time when biblical תרומה Trumah
exists, she can't eat anything because once she eats something she'll assume,
oh I'm legitimately married to a כהן Kohen and she'll come to
eat other stuff. So at the time of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash he doesn't eat anything, but nowadays she can at least eat
rabbinic תרומה, Trumah, there's no possible transgression דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Yes, Charlie.
So if תרומה Trumah is rabbinic today that would imply that the
obligation to separate tithes is rabbinic which would represent a- that would
be rabbinic.
Yeah, so that is the quest- that is the question.
That's according to this גמרא. Gemara. It's not clear that we rule
that way but yeah, meaning there's two- one is the question about
whether, you know, קדושה ראשונה קידשה לעתיד לבוא, Kedusha rishona kidesha l'atid
lavo, the קדושה kedusha of the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash as
it applies to the status of the land for תרומות ומעשרות Trumos
v'Ma'asros applies for all future times even after the חורבן. Churban. This
גמרא Gemara presumably assumes not, but many גמרות Gemaras assume yes. And
then there's a separate issue that the רמב"ם Rambam brings about which
is saying, which is an idea called ביאת כולכם, bi'as kulchem, that
even at the time of עזרא Ezra maybe it wasn't biblical because
the
land...
No we don't even bother with פאה peah today.
Don't even bother with פאה? peah? Is that true?
Yeah, it's not even in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch.
Well, the fact that it's not in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
is not relevant. I don't know, why wouldn't it be true? Why
wouldn't
Israeli farmers do פאה? peah?
Well, for most of the last few thousand years there weren't really
any Jewish farmers.
So what? I don't know where, just cause I wouldn't make any
assumptions just cause it's not in שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, I assume
there is פאה peah nowadays for Israeli farmers. It's an interesting thing
to look at, to explore what's actually done by, you know, in
on religious קיבוצים. kibbutzim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, so that's ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, it's
a ספק. safek. So only at the time when there is nowadays,
when there's no possible דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, does he let this woman eat
the תרומה. truma. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebbe Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan says, אף מחזירה בחזה ושוק, af machzira b'chazeh v'shok, no, שקידש
ויאכל קדשים, she-kiddesh v'yochal kodshim, it is-
this אנדרוגינוס androgynos is halakhically a male and she can even eat
קדשים. kodshim. אמר ליה Amar leh רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan לריש לקיש,
l'Reish Lakish, רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
מי סברת תרומה בזמן הזה דרבנן? mi savaras truma bizman hazeh d'rabbanan?
Do
you really hold תרומה truma nowadays
is דרבנן? rabbinic? Interesting, right, because that to me that would seem
to be like a secondary concern of their debate. Their real debate
is what's the status of an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, of an androgyne, and
that therefore translates into what they assume his wife can eat. But
here where he's critiquing him is not on his position that an
androgyne is male, but in his idea that there's a difference nowadays
than the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because nowadays it's
all דרבנן. rabbinic. So that he's challenged. Do you really hold that
תרומה truma nowadays is all דרבנן? rabbinic? אמר ליה אין, Amar leh
in, says yes, שאני שונה she-ani shoneh because I teach עיגול בעיגולים
עולה igul b'igulim olah or עולה, oleh, that a- an עיגול, igul,
like a round of pressed figs, I think it is, I always
get confused. Yeah, is it figs or dates? I always get confused.
It's say- figs, ah, I'm actually getting it right. Okay, a round
of pressed figs, you know, standard sort of things that they do.
Nowadays though, when you- because nowadays you go to the supermarket, you
get these things of pressed figs, right? I see those like those
circles, those those like, yeah, you get like those- those. Those are
figs? Oh, that's right, the dates are- those are dried figs, but
they're so- Okay, okay, fine, so that's what an עיגול igul is,
pressed figs. Anyway, here is the הלכה. halakha. What happens if you
get something of תרומה truma mixed up with other things of תרומה?
truma? What do you need to create ביטול? bittel? And the הלכה
halakha is that you need a hundred as opposed to sixty, which
is the normal rule, here you need a hundred,
and when it is בטל, battel, the phrase used is עולה oleh
or עולה, olah, that it is- it's עולה באחד ומאה, oleh b'echad
u'me'ah, that in one and a hundred it is בטל, battel, it's
just- that's just the technical word that's used in this context to
say
בטל. battel. So, now, the other thing you need to know is
that when you're dealing with something that is חשוב, chashuv, something that
in its- on its self, right? The whole idea that ביטול bittel
works is that things become all like mixed up and you look
at it as a collective, like I've got a hundred apples here,
so you don't look at it as- and therefore it's one big
bale of apples, so one of them is a problem, is תרומה,
truma, but okay, it's insignificant in this whole big bale of apples.
But when things are significant, you don't look at them as a
group, you look at each thing individually. Like you wouldn't say, you
know, you know, I've got like a parking lot full of cars
and it's all one big jumble of cars, right? Each car is
separate, right? You don't look at them all as a collective.
So therefore, similarly, when you have an object that you- that is
significant in itself, it's not בטל battel because then you don't look
at it as part of a whole big group and it loses
its significance because it's overwhelmed by everything else, you look at each
object in the group independently. Okay, so, and now, and that normally
there's different ways of defining what makes something significant. The idea we're
going to be dealing with here is a principle called דבר שבמנין,
davar she-biminyan, something that is counted. So things that you count by
number, as opposed to when you do it by weight or volume
or basket, I can buy a basket of eggs, I can buy,
you know, I can buy things by their weight and so on.
But things that you would only buy by the number is considered
that therefore each one is individually significant, and therefore a house, well,
okay, car is a little less extreme example than a house, and
therefore,
but you know, I mean, chairs, right? You could buy six chairs
or whatever,
you don't buy a bushel of chairs. Right, so the funny thing
is that there are some things that you sell by number that
are not individually significant, like I mean, eggs, we don't sell eggs
by the basket, but they used to, right? But anyway,
but you- but anyway, but you- but anyway, so things that are
sold by number are considered individually significant and therefore not is just
part of a group and therefore they're not בטל. batel. So those
are the basic rules. Now,
he says that I have I teach a ברייתא beraita that says
עיגול בעיגולין. iggul b'iggulin. Now he's assuming that an עיגול iggul is
something that is דבר שבמניין, davar she'b'minyan, something that is counted because
you say how many rounds of dates do you want, of figs
do you want? So and if that gets mixed up, one of
תרומה terumah with others, I say עולה oleh that it could be
בטל batel if it's one in a hundred. Now why is that?
That should be the principle that דבר שבמניין davar she'b'minyan is not
בטל. batel. So it must be that the answer is that it's
because תרומה terumah nowadays, if it's a תרומה terumah round of pressed
figs that gets mixed up, תרומה terumah nowadays is rabbinic and therefore
we could be lenient because it's all rabbinic. But if it were
really דאורייתא, deoraita, we wouldn't allow ביטול bittul there, even in a
hundred, because it's דבר שבמניין, davar she'b'minyan, it's a significant thing.
Really? So דרבנן derabbanan the laws of ביטול bittul will apply to
something that...
Yeah, so will things be more able to be בטל batel because
they're rabbinic? The general answer is no. Okay, there are some times
where you say yes because there's a type of a ספק safek
and you allow yourself to say, well, it's all rabbinic, we can
assume X happened rather than Y. But when it's not a ספק,
safek, when it's ביטול, bittul, the general rule is we don't distinguish
between דרבנן derabbanan and דאורייתא. deoraita. But the גמרא Gemara plays with
the possibility that we might.
There might be a type of סניף. snif. Yeah, exactly, and דרבנן.
derabbanan.
Well, yeah, although here he's not saying סניף, snif, but again, להלכה
l'halacha we don't, we're not more מיקל meikel by דרבנן derabbanan for
ביטול, bittul, but here he assumes we are. So he says, yes,
I hold it's rabbinic and my proof is that a round of
pressed figs of תרומה terumah can be בטל batel and we don't
say the normal rule that דבר שבמניין davar she'b'minyan is not
בטל. batel. אמר ליה, Amar lei, והלא אני שונה חתיכה בחתיכה עולה,
vehalo ani shoneh chatichah b'chatichah oleh. that even by biblical things, even
if you have a nice chunk of a nice steak of like
of a, you know, of קדשים, kodashim, and it gets mixed up
with other steaks, that it's בטל. batel. And a steak is also
דבר שבמניין, davar she'b'minyan, right? A steak is also something that's חשוב.
chashuv. So you can't prove, and קדשים kodashim is clearly דאורייתא. deoraita.
So basically you can't prove from the fact that ביטול bittul works
with a דבר שבמניין davar she'b'minyan that it's rabbinic. Because I got
a ברייתא beraita that says that ביטול bittul works with דבר שבמניין
davar she'b'minyan even if you're dealing with like קדשים. kodashim. So clearly
it's not because it's rabbinic, clearly it's because actually דבר שבמניין davar
she'b'minyan maybe could be בטל. batel. Okay, so your inference is incorrect
because I have a ברייתא beraita that says even by biblical things
it's בטל. batel. So let's take a look. Right, so you can't
prove that it's rabbinic. Exactly. And
so he says, אמר ליה, Amar lei,
והלא אני שונה vehalo ani shoneh חתיכה בחתיכה עולה. chatichah b'chatichah oleh,
מי סברת
כל שדרכו לימנות שנינו? Mi savrat kol shedarko limanot shaninu? Here's your
mistake, רש לקיש. Reish Lakish. You think when the ברייתא beraita says
that a דבר שבמניין davar she'b'minyan is not בטל, batel, you think
the text of the ברייתא beraita is everything that is quoted, everything
that
its way is to be counted, כל שדרכו לימנות kol shedarko limanot
is not בטל. batel. But that's not the right text of the
ברייתא. beraita. We're going to see the ברייתא beraita in a minute.
את שדרכו לימנות שנינו. Et shedarko limanot shaninu. The text of the
ברייתא beraita is that which is counted, not everything which is counted.
What's the difference between that which is counted and everything which is
counted? So what about things that are sometimes done by number and
sometimes done in other ways? Sometimes you can buy a bushel of
apples and you can buy 10 apples. You can buy, you know,
a basket of eggs and you can buy them individually. If it's
sometimes counted, does that make it חשוב, chashuv, or is it חשוב
chashuv and not בטל batel only if it's only counted? If it's
only sold by number? So he says, מר גרס את שדרכו לימנות,
Mar garas et shedarko limanot, only that which is only sold by
number is something that is not בטל. batel. And you think it's
everything, even if it's sometimes sold, anything that is numbered, even if
it's sometimes numbered, is not בטל. batel. So basically you look at
this idea that a round of figs is בטל batel and you
infer "Aha, it's because it's rabbinic." You're wrong! It has nothing to
do with it being rabbinic, it has to do with the fact
that it's not only sold by number, that you are wrong about
the, about what types of things are not בטל. batel. These things
are בטל batel because they're sometimes sold other ways. So you're completely
wrong to infer from this that it's because it's rabbinic. Okay. מה
היא? Mai hi? What is this thing that you're referring to? This
משנה Mishnah about כל kol or את שדרכו? et shedarko? דתנן במתניתין:
Detnan bematnitin: מי שהיו לו חבילי תלתן של כלאי הכרם. Mi shehayu
lo chavilei tiltan shel kilaei hakerem. Somebody has bundles of תלתן. tiltan.
I think Rashi says that's fenugreek? Yeah, fenugreek. Now you understand exactly
what I'm talking about. Okay. Clover.
Whatever. Of כלאיים. kilayim. ידלקו. Yidalku. You have to burn them because
that's what you do about כלאיים kilayim that's mixed with things that
grew together with wine. ידלקו. Yidalku. They have to be burned. נתערבו
באחרות, Nitarvu b'acherot, if they got mixed up with other bundles of
clover, fenugreek, that is not כלאיים, kilayim, כולם ידלקו. kulam yidalku. You
burn them all. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Rabbi
Meir says because it's not
בטל. batel. וחכמים אומרים יעלו באחד ומאתים. Vachachamim omrim ya'alu b'echad umatayim.
Sometimes we even say it's never בטל. batel. So by כלאים kilayim
we go by one in 200, by תרומה terumah it's one in
100. So the חכמים chachamim say it is בטל. batel. Now why
does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say it's not בטל? batel? שהיה רבי
מאיר אומר shehayah Rabbi Meir omer because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used
to say כל שדרכו למנות, kol shedarko limnot, and here's the question:
is it את שדרכו למנות et shedarko limnot or כל שדרכו למנות?
kol shedarko limnot? But we're going with רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's גרסא,
girsa, I'm sorry, with ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish's גרסא. girsa. את... Et...
I'm sorry... anything that is sometimes, that is counted, meaning even if
it's sometimes counted, מקדש mekadesh sanctifies. Not as a good thing, meaning
מקדש mekadesh means transfers its forbidden status to everything else and prevent...
it is not בטל, batel, everything is אסור. asur. So you hear
here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying it's something that is counted is
not בטל, batel, and ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish's גרסא girsa is something
that is sometimes counted, that's, you know, anything that's ever counted. Whereas
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's גרסא girsa is things that are sold only
by counting, and that is the big debate.
וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, the sages disagree with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
because they say it is בטל. batel. And they have, and their
idea of what is a דבר חשוב, davar chashuv, something that is
independent identity and not בטל, batel, is a much more limited category.
אינו מקדש אלא שישה דברים בלבד, eino mekadesh ela shishah devarim bilvad,
only six things are not בטל. batel. What are those six things?
רבי עקיבא אומר שבעה, Rabbi Akiva omer shivah, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says seven. אלו הן, elu hen, and these are they: אגוזי פרך,
egozei parach, nuts of Parach, which either is a name of a
place or תוספות Tosafot says it's like a type of... means cracking
nuts or something like that, I don't know what they are. רימוני
בדן, rimonei badan, pomegranates from Badan. וחביות סתומות, vechaviyot stumot, sealed barrels
of wine. וחלפי תרדין, vechalfai teradin, something... something of beets, I don't
know what your English says there.
Shoots of beets.
Shoots of beets, okay. וקלחי כרוב, vekalchei keruv, like heads of cabbage.
ודלעת יוונית, vedila'at yevanit, and Greek gourd. If I had to guess
the six things that are חשוב chashuv by themselves and not in
a, and not just grouped together in a big bundle of other
things, I don't know if I would have imagined these. But okay,
even for the
ancient world... What?
Seal? Barrels? Yeah, you do count them. וחכמים vechachamim are saying you
don't. The חכמים chachamim are saying it's a subset of what you,
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, says. You, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, says that
the things that are not בטל batel is things that are counted,
whether always counted, whether only counted, or sometimes counted. We think that's
too big of a category. We think it's a much smaller category,
is presumably a subset. So they're not saying you don't count these
things, they're saying it's a subset of your bigger category, רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. But again, what's so significant about these? I have no
idea. רמב"ם, Rambam, when he brings down this הלכה, halacha, says basically
anything similar that is חשוב chashuv in that place and at that
time. You know, obviously it's not like הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe
miSinai these six things. רבי עקיבא מוסיף, Rabbi Akiva mosif, and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva adds: אף ככרות של בעל הבית, af kikarot shel
ba'al habayit, even home-baked bread. That you understand. Oh, home-baked חלה. challah.
Okay, anyway. So,
alright, anyway. הראויות לערלה ערלה, hare'uyot le'orlah orlah, those things that we
could be talking about that they were ערלה, orlah, meaning those things
that are fruit-based, which are cases of ערלה, orlah, like the wine
which comes obviously from the grapes and what else did we have
here? Oh, and the nuts and the pomegranates. So that would be
a scenario that they were ערלה orlah and that they were mixed
up with other things that weren't ערלה. orlah. וכלאי הכרם, vekilai hakerem,
and those things that could be כלאים kilayim that are more like
a vegetable-based, the gourd and the beets and so on. כלאי הכרם
kilai hakerem would be in a scenario of כלאי הכרם.
kilai hakerem. These items can be בטל? batel?
No, the ones that we mentioned cannot. Either things according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that are counted, or things according to the חכמים,
chachamim, a particular list of six or seven things, those are things
that are not בטל. batel.
How come it says אינו מקדש? eino mekadesh?
אינו מקדש אלא. eino mekadesh ela. מקדש mekadesh is a bad thing.
מקדש mekadesh means makes the whole mixture forbidden. The only thing that
makes the whole mixture forbidden is not your whole category of things
that are counted, but
just these six or seven things.
Right.
So,
רבי יוחנן סבר, Rabbi Yochanan savar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that
the position in רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... it's fascinating that the assumption
is that we rule like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right? Because there's
a חכמים chachamim here, there's a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva here, but
somehow the assumption is that we're talking within רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
and that's relevant to their other discussion. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says the rule is את שדרכו למנות שנינו, et shedarko limnot shaninu,
things that are only counted. ריש לקיש סבר: Resh Lakish savar: כל
שדרכו למנות שנינו, kol shedarko limnot shaninu, that things that are, anything
that is counted, meaning even sometimes counted. So again, how is this
relevant? ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says:
I will prove to you that תרומה terumah is rabbinic because a
round of pressed figs is בטל batel even though it's counted. So
obviously that's rabbinic. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: No, that's not
why it's בטל. batel. It's בטל batel because it's not את שדרכו
למנות. et shedarko למנות. It's not sold only by number, even if
it's sometimes sold by number, and therefore it's בטל. batel. It has
nothing to do with it being rabbinic. Your category of things that
aren't בטל batel are way too big. These types of things are
בטל. batel. And what's his proof that these types of things are
בטל? batel? Because he's got a ברייתא braisa that teaches about a
steak of קדשים kodshim that's clearly דאורייתא d'Oraisa that's בטל. batel. Let's
just see that. מאי חתיכה בחתיכה? mai chaticha bechaticha? What's his category
of these sort of the chops of meat, of the chunk of
meat that is בטל batel even though it's sometimes sold by number?
דתניא detanya we תנא tana ברייתא. baraita. חתיכה של חטאת טמאה, chaticha
shel chatat t'me'ah, you have a nice chunk of a חטאת chatat
meat that is טמא tamei and therefore can't be eaten, שנתערבה במאה
חתיכות של חטאות טהורות, shenitarva b'me'ah chatichot shel chatatot tehorot, it got
mixed up with a hundred chunks of טהור tahor חטאת chatat meat,
וכן v'chen and so too again the rule of one in a
hundred, וכן פרוסה של לחם הפנים טמאה v'chen prusa shel lechem hapanim
t'me'ah or a פרוסה prusa of of the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim,
of the bread that goes on the שולחן shulchan on the table
in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that is טמא tamei and therefore
can't be eaten because it's קדשים, kadashim, שנתערבה במאה פרוסות של לחם
הפנים טהורות, shenitarva b'me'ah prusot shel lechem hapanim tehorot, it got mixed
up with a hundred טהור tahor pieces of the לחם הפנים. lechem
hapanim. תעלה, ta'aleh, presumably you had to divide it amongst the
כהנים. kohanim. תעלה, ta'aleh, so it's בטל. batel. רבי יהודה אומר לא
תעלה, Rebbi Yehuda omer lo ta'aleh, it's not בטל. batel. So we're
worried about רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda in a minute, but you see
according to the חכמים chachamim it's בטל. batel. And רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan assumes that a חתיכה chaticha is something that you would be
selling by number. So that's his proof against ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
אבל, aval, but now let's just finish the ברייתא. baraita. חתיכה של
חטאת טהורה שנתערבה במאה חתיכות של חולין טהורות, chaticha shel chatat tehorah
shenitarva b'me'ah chatichot shel chullin tehorot, if it's all טהור, tahor,
חטאת chatat with חולין, chullin, but now it's just a question, do
I treat it like this חטאת chatat here and only a כהן
kohen can eat it, or do I am I allowed to even
have a ישראל? Yisrael? You wouldn't have to throw it all out
because nothing is טמא, tamei, but it's a חטאת chatat with חולין.
chullin. וכן פרוסה של לחם הפנים טהורה שנתערבה במאה פרוסות של חולין
טהורות, v'chen prusa shel lechem hapanim tehorah shenitarva b'me'ah prusot shel chullin
tehorot, or piece of the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim got mixed up
with a hundred pieces of unsanctified bread. So again, it's not like
everything would be אסור, assur, but the question is, can it only
be eaten by a כהן kohen or not? So in that case,
דברי הכל לא תעלה, divrei hakol lo ta'aleh, everybody says it's not
בטל. batel. Why not? What makes it different? So רש"י Rashi basically
says, and then there's a whole long discussion רש"י Rashi tells us
what are the parameters of this, but in that type of a
case it's like a combination of factors. Number one is, even though
it's כל שדרכו לימנות kol shedarko limanot and not את שדרכו לימנות,
et shedarko limanot, right? It's something, meaning even though it's something that
is not only counted, but it does have some חשיבות, chashivut, it's
sometimes counted, meaning you know, it's in this gray area, sometimes counted
but not exclusively counted. So normally we would say בטל. batel. But
you combine that with the fact that even if we don't say
ביטול bitul here, you're not going to have to throw it out.
All you're going to have to do is have a כהן kohen
eat it. So therefore, given that it's not such a terrible consequence
here to say it's not בטל, batel, and that the thing is
somewhat חשוב, chashuv, here we're going to sort of say, eh, we
won't say ביטול. bitul. Now again, that's pretty funny, right? Similar to
the point of like are we going to say it by דרבנן
derabbanan as opposed to דאורייתא? de'oraita? Normally we don't sort of make
these judgment calls by ביטול. bitul. Is it a bad consequence? Not
a bad consequence? Like we have very clear rules. Anyway, that's the
way רש"י Rashi reads it here, because the consequence is not so
severe in this type of case. In the end, and it's somewhat
חשוב, chashuv, we're going to say that it's not בטל. batel. But
we're going to bracket that. That's that's interesting and תוספות Tosafot has
another explanation. What's relevant for us is that in the beginning it
says that even though it's a חתיכה, chaticha, it is בטל. batel.
And רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says, you see? We're talking about biblical
because it's חטאת, chatat, and we're talking about a חתיכה chaticha which
I think, says רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, something that is sometimes counted.
And nevertheless, it's בטל. batel. Why is that? It must be that
as long as it's not exclusively counted, even if it's sometimes counted,
you can still have ביטול. bitul. Okay, so let's just see that
תנא מיהת, tana mihat, so we see nevertheless, רישא תעלה, reisha ta'aleh,
that it's בטל. batel. And there's a proof against ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, a חתיכה chaticha can be בטל. batel. So even though it
is sometimes counted. So what's the how would ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
answer
that? So אמר רב אסי בריה דרב הונא, amar Rav Assi breih
deRav Huna, בנימוחה, binimucha, we're talking about that it is dissolved. Yes,
it says that it's a חתיכה, chaticha, but it does not mean
that you have five you have five steaks in front of you.
חתיכה chaticha got mixed up and you ground it all into hamburger
meat. Okay, so it's a case where it's no longer a חתיכה
chaticha and that's how ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would answer it. So
on the face of it, does it sound like a חתיכה chaticha
can be בטל? batel? Does it sound like something that sometimes is
counted can be בטל batel and it's a proof to רבי יוחנן?
Rebbi Yochanan? Yes. But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish will say it's talking
about a case where it no longer retains its independent identity, it's
been ground up and that's why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say
ביטול bitul works here. Yes, Michael?
What about תרומה דרבנן? terumah derabbanan? So like he said that it
depends on the תנא. tana. מן התורה? min haTorah? דזמן הזה? d'zman
hazeh? Right. But what about the location, can it not be like
you know, those outlying like you know, areas
of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that?
Yeah, that could also be, yeah. And then practically, again, צריך ביטול,
tzarich bitul, like what's the other are there any other differences between
תרומה דרבנן terumah derabbanan and דאורייתא? de'oraita? If we...
Yeah, there are a lot about how do you deal with cases
about ספק safek and how do you deal with cases of טומאה,
tumah, but again, you're like you're asking too big of a question
right now. Yes, Dove?
I was interested, it got ground up, it lost its identity, you
can't distinguish, I'm trying to figure out why מין במינו min b'mino
is not part of the categories here. How does that cut into
this?
Well, okay, so again, everybody knows too much right now. So anyway,
בטלה, batela, מין במינו, min b'mino, sometimes it's a basis for a
leniency, but actually it's important to know that in these
הלכות halachot that... actually we're more strict when it's like mixed up
with like, and there we actually say that the need for a
hundred or two hundred is only when it's something mixed up with
something of its own kind. When it's mixed up with something of
a different kind, in that case it's בטל batel once it no
longer gives taste and ששים shishim and so on. So that tends
to be sometimes we're more stringent when it's of its own kind,
though basic logic is, you know, we go two extremes with מין
במינו. min b'mino. You could say, if something is אינו מינו, aino
mino, it's something with something different, like a little, you drop a
little bit of, I don't know, you know, milk in your chicken
soup, and in that type of a case you say, well, it
loses its identity. If you can't taste it, it started off as
something distinct, but now there's none of its distinctiveness left, so it
loses its identity once it can no longer be tasted. Let's say
you drop מין במינו, min b'mino, a little bit of טרף treif
chicken into your chicken soup, or let's make, let's even say that
it's not distinct, a little טרף treif chicken soup into your kosher
chicken soup. So you could say it's בטל batel right away because
it never has a distinct identity, so that's an opinion that מין
במינו min b'mino is בטל batel even biblically even immediately. There's, you
know, you don't even need ששים. shishim. No, but even רוב, rov,
you don't even need ששים. shishim. The other approach is is that
no, because it never was distinct, it never loses its identity, so
it's always there. You always have chicken here. You don't have something
other than chicken that stopped existing. You had chicken and you had
chicken and you still have chicken, so it's always there. That's רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position that מין במינו min b'mino is לא בטל.
lo batel. So therefore, in cases where we're more strict, like we
require a hundred or two hundred, we only do it by מינו.
mino. By אינו מינו, aino mino, we can't say the thing is
around once it can't be tasted. It started with a distinct identity
and it lost its distinct identity and therefore it stops existing. But
when we could say you need a hundred times or two hundred
times or whatever, that we could say by מין במינו, min b'mino,
because there we could say it always is around, it never lost
its identity, and if you want it to lose its identity, you
need to make it a trivial, you know, you need to make
it of only trivial significance, you need to turn it into a
trace quantity. And the only way you can turn it into a
trace quantity is if it's less than one percent or less than
a half of a percent and so on. So that's why we
tend to be in these scenarios more strict by מין במינו. min
b'mino. So since you raised that, I will say that that's relevant
also because when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says here that it's לא
בטל, lo batel, remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it's לא בטל
lo batel in one and a hundred, right in these cases about
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and so on that's טמא? tamei? So
רש"י Rashi says the reason is is because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is the one who's normally of the position that מין במינו לא
בטל. min b'mino lo batel. That's so that's why רש"י Rashi says
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is being more strict. תוספות Tosafot doesn't like
that, but whatever, I won't tell you why, but anyway תוספות Tosafot
has another explanation for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay. So now let's
take a look at as the גמרא Gemara continues. So
where we gotten to now? We've gotten to that the let's remember
the first debate, which I think is is the, you know, very
interesting one in the context of the משנה, Mishna, is an אנדרוגינוס
androgynos a man or a ספק? safek? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
he's a man, so if he's married to a woman she's definitely
married and she can eat תרומה terumah and חזה ושוק chazeh v'shok
the whole thing. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says he's a ספק safek
and therefore the woman who eats תרומה terumah on his behalf is
only talking about nowadays where there's no such thing as תרומה דאורייתא.
terumah de'oraisa. Okay, and then
the that turned into a debate of is תרומה terumah nowadays דאורייתא
de'oraisa or דרבנן? d'rabanan? And ריש לקיש Resh Lakish wanted to prove
it from the fact that ביטול bittul works in certain cases. And
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that's absolutely no proof. ביטול bittul works
even by דאורייתא de'oraisa in those cases. And then it turns out
what they're debating is not only is תרומה terumah nowadays דאורייתא de'oraisa
or דרבנן, d'rabanan, but it's rooted in somehow and indirectly in a
debate about when things are not בטל. batel. ריש לקיש... Resh Lakish...
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says things are often לא בטל, lo batel,
even if it sometimes counts it's לא בטל. lo batel. So therefore
if it's going to be בטל batel it proves it's דרבנן. d'rabanan.
And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you got it wrong, you know,
things are it's only a rare situation that things are לא בטל,
lo batel, only things that are exclusively counted. So if something is
בטל batel it's not because it's rabbinic, it's because it's not in
that very small category of things that are exclusively counted. So that's
the second debate of whether of what are the parameters of what
cases prevent ביטול. bittul. So now let's see as the גמרא Gemara
continues. So the גמרא Gemara to deal with this case of the
חתיכה chaticha that is בטל batel which is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, it's for
ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, it turned it into a case of hamburger,
not of a distinct state. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
ei hachi if that's the case, מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama
d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason? If now it's all hamburger, then why
would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if it was a distinct steak we
could understand that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's לא בטל lo
batel because, you know, it's distinct, that's חשוב. chashuv. But if it's
all hamburger, why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying that it's לא
בטל lo batel in the ברייתא braita he quoted? So רבי יהודה
לטעמיה Rabbi Yehuda l'taimei and here we go to what we were
just discussing דאמר מין במינו לא בטל. d'amar min b'mino lo batel.
That's not because it's חשוב chashuv and it's distinct, that's because it's
מין במינו. min b'mino. Okay. אבל נמח מאי? aval nimach mai? So
the גמרא Gemara saying
fine, but what would you ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say if it
hadn't been dissolved, I'm going to say hamburger, what would be the
הלכה? halacha?
It mean like לחה בלחה lacha b'lacha or whatever it is?
No, no, no, it means it's לחה בלחה, lacha b'lacha, it's all
mixed up together, it's not a distinct piece. So if it's not
hamburger, מאי, mai, what would you say ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? לא
תעלה, lo ta'aleh, then it wouldn't be בטל batel because that would
be something that would be sometimes counted. So if that's true, עד
דתניא, ad d'tanya, if that's... if the ברייתא braita when the ברייתא
braita gives the contrast, אבל חתיכה שחטאת טהורה שנתערבה במאה חתיכות שחולין
טהורות לא תעלה, aval chaticha shechatat tehorah shenit'arba beme'ah chatichot shechulin tehorot
lo ta'aleh,
when it gives the contrast of something which isn't בטל, battel, when
it's all טהור, tahor, it's just חולין chulin that got mixed up
with nonsense, I mean קדשים kodashim that got mixed up with חולין
chulin with non-sanctified, right? And there it's not בטל battel because as
רש״י Rashi says there's not a big loss. Why did it have
to run to that case to say it's not בטל? battel? נפלוג
ונתני בדידי? niflog venisni bedidi?
According to you ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, you could have made a
distinction in the case itself of sometimes it's not being בטל. battel.
במידי דאמרן be'midi de'amran meaning when is it בטל? battel? בשנימוח, beshenimoach,
when it's turned into hamburger meat and therefore it's not distinct. אבל
לא נימוח, aval lo nimoach, if it's not turned into hamburger meat,
לא, lo, it wouldn't be בטל battel according to you ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish because it would be something that would be sometimes counted.
לא תעלה. lo ta'aleh. So if we want to give an example
of לא בטל, lo battel, we shouldn't have had to run to
this case of a different scenario. In the same scenario it wouldn't
be בטל battel if you just didn't make it into hamburger meat.
So the גמרא Gemara says טהור בטהור עדיף ליה. tahor betahor adif
leh.
No, it would rather show you a case where everything is טהור
tahor and even so and and, you know,
by virtue of the fact that everything is טהור tahor that's why
it's not בטל. battel. That's the case it would rather give you,
you know, that's a bigger חידוש chiddush somehow than a case when
it's not turned
into, turned into, what do you call it, that
it's not turned into hamburger meat ground together.
Rather than
going to a case of not hamburger meat and a steak which
isn't בטל, battel, it would rather tell you the חידוש chiddush that
even when it is turned into hamburger meat it will not be
בטל battel if we're dealing with everything is טהור. tahor. Okay, so
let's take a look. טהור בטהור עדיף
ליה.
tahor
betahor adif leh. It'd rather show you a case that even though
it is hamburger meat it won't be בטל battel if everything is
טהור. tahor. עדיף ליה. adif leh. Okay. ולריש לקיש מאי שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא? uleresh lakish mai shna reisha umai shna seifa? So
now what is the difference? Why is it in the beginning that
it's not בטל? battel? But when everything is טהור, tahor, I'm sorry,
I got it wrong. When it's hamburger meat it is בטל battel
in the beginning when it's a טמא tamei mixed up with a
טהור. tahor. But when everything is טהור, tahor, it's not בטל. battel.
What's the difference? Why in the סיפא seifa if it's all hamburger
meat, right, that's what we said, it's all hamburger meat and therefore
in the רישא reisha it's בטל battel when it's something טמא tamei
mixed up with something טהור. tahor. But if that's true, then if
it's all טהור tahor it should also be בטל. battel. Why is
it not בטל battel in the
סיפא? seifa? אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי.
amar rav sheshet brei
de'rav idi.
That's what רש״י Rashi said, but רש״י Rashi said that's also because
it was חשוב chashuv and distinct. But now that we're saying it's
all hamburger meat, there's not a good reason to say it's not
בטל battel in the סיפא. seifa. So אמר רב ששת בריה דרב
אידי רישא בטומאת משקין דרבנן סיפא דאורייתא. amar rav sheshet brei de'rav
idi reisha betum'at mashkin derabbanan seifa de'orayta. Okay, here's the reason, because
in the beginning we were talking about the fact that it was
only טמא tamei because it touched some type of a טמא tamei
liquid. Okay, and therefore it's really, you know, not so problematic, right?
Yes, the תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah or the steak is טמא, tamei,
but only because it touched some liquid that became טמא tamei from
a שני sheni and because of special rabbinic rules it got upgraded
and I won't go into the details and therefore it's only טומאה
דרבנן. tum'ah derabbanan. And since it's טומאה דרבנן tum'ah derabbanan we'll allow
ביטול bittul to work. But in the סיפא seifa we're not dealing
with a דרבנן, derabbanan, we're dealing with the fact that you have
a real piece of לחם הפנים lechem hapanim or a real חטאת
chatat that got mixed up with חולין. chulin. And there, if you
go ahead and say that it is בטל, battel, what's somebody going
to do? A טמא tamei person will eat it
because it's hamburger meat.
Right, hamburger meat, what I say, a steak, whatever, hamburger meat it
got mixed up, okay, but but part of it is part of
it is from קדשים. kodashim. So if you say that it is
בטל, battel, a טמא tamei person is going to eat it. If
a טמא tamei person eats קדשים, kodashim, that's an איסור כרת, issur
karet, that's an איסור דאורייתא. issur de'orayta. Okay, so in the beginning,
it's only a כהן kohen is going to eat it. The question
is something was טמא, tamei, can we let him eat it? All
right, it was only a rabbinic טומאה, tum'ah, really biblically everything is
fine, let him eat it. In the סיפא, seifa, we want to
know can a non-כהן kohen eat it? And a non-כהן kohen can
eat it even when he's טמא? tamei? That's a biblical issue. In
that case we're going to say don't eat it, we're dealing with
biblical things, ביטול bittul will not work. So according to this, we
are actually saying that the reason we allow ביטול bittul to work
here even though, you know, is only because we're dealing with a
rabbinic area. All right, I think I've managed to successfully lose everybody.
Let's take a, no, the rabbinic what's a new, part of the
argument is it's the rabbinic element is a rabbinic טומאה. tum'ah.
Right, let's take a, yeah, that's but let's take a step back.
Hold on, hold on, we're going to take a step back, okay.
Here
here we got the case. Okay, first you have a hundred steaks,
okay, got a hundred steaks. Okay, and these are all חטאת טהורה,
chatat tehorah, these are all חטאת טהורה, chatat tehorah, okay? And you
got mixed up with them one steak
of חטאת טמאה. chatat tmeiah. Okay, of course if it was red
you wouldn't be able to know which one it was, right? Okay,
that's that's the רישא, reisha, okay? This is the רישא, reisha, okay?
And the סיפא seifa is not חטאת טהורה chatas tehora and חטאת
טמאה, chatas tmeiah, but the סיפא seifa is you've got a hundred
things of חולין, chulin,
right? These are all חולין, chulin, and gets mixed up with them
one thing of חטאת טהורה, chatas tehora, okay? And we say that
here it's בטל, batel,
we say here it's בטל batel and here it's
אין בטל, ein batel, not בטל, batel, okay? So what's the difference?
So when we were in רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan land, we said,
okay, things are חשוב chashuv here, they're quasi-חשוב. chashuv. It's sometimes counted,
not always counted. So the real הלכה halacha is that it's בטל,
batel, and that's this הלכה, halacha, that it's בטל. batel. And therefore
you're allowed to eat it even though if you knew it's the
piece of the חטאת טמאה chatas tmeiah you can't eat that piece,
you can go ahead and eat it. Okay, that's the real, that's
the real הלכה. halacha. Here, even though it should be בטל, batel,
since things are quasi-חשוב, chashuv, you know, and it's not a big
loss, just get a כהן kohein to eat it, it's not like
you have to throw it all out, not בטל. batel. That's the
way רש״י Rashi explained it. But now what do we say? According
to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, we say, wait a minute, according to
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, this shouldn't be בטל. batel. They're independent pieces
here. Why is this בטל? batel? Right? It's something that's sometimes counted.
Why is it בטל? batel? So he said, okay, the reason it's
בטל batel is because you turned it all into hamburger meat. Okay,
so it's all a big mix and that's why it's בטל, batel,
okay? And it's that you don't have independent pieces. You turned it
into hamburger meat and that's why it's בטל. batel. Okay, says the
גמרא, Gemara, but if you turned that into hamburger meat, right, then
you've turned this into hamburger meat. So, well, because there's רישא reisha
and סיפא seifa talking about the same case, because if it wasn't
hamburger meat we could have said that this case also isn't בטל
batel if they're not hamburger meat, right? So that's the point, we
say even though, even though it's hamburger meat, if it's not hamburger
meat it won't be בטל batel because each piece is significant. But
even if it's hamburger meat, it's not gonna be בטל batel in
the סיפא, seifa, it's not gonna be בטל batel in the סיפא.
seifa. So the גמרא Gemara says, well why not? Don't tell me,
oh, you can just get a כהן kohein to eat it. That's
a good argument if there's a reason for it not to be
בטל, batel, right, if things are independent. But if here it's all
hamburger meat, why shouldn't it be בטל? batel? That's the גמרא's Gemara
question. And the גמרא Gemara says you can just get a non-כהן
kohein to eat it? Yeah, exactly, even though it's mostly חולין. chulin.
Right. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is, here's the difference. Here, you're,
now again, it doesn't explain why we shouldn't be בטל, batel, but
for some reason we don't want ביטול bitul to work here. Not
exactly clear why not, that's sort of the unanswered question.
But we'll let
ביטול bitul work
in this case because the problematic piece only became טמא tamei with
a דרבנן טומאה.
derabbanan tumah. And therefore you're not even dealing with such an איסור
issur here. Okay, what's gonna happen? It's all gonna be treated like
חטאת, chatas, a כהן kohein is gonna eat it, and he'll eat
this problematic piece with it. Okay, but it's only דרבנן טומאה, derabbanan
tumah, it's not such a big problem. Even though it's קדשים? kodashim?
Well, but he'll, he'll eat it because the rest is קדשים kodashim
too. So it's all, it's only a דרבנן derabbanan problem, a כהן
kohein will eat it, and therefore we'll allow ביטול bitul to work.
Down here, okay, down here, if you say this thing, what's gonna
happen if you say it's בטל? batel? A non-כהן kohen will eat
it, right, because it's בטל, batel, and he might even be טמא
tamei when he eats it.
You're dealing with a biblical problem.
So since here you're dealing with a biblical problem, we're not gonna
allow ביטול. bitul. Now it still begs the question why, okay, I
understand this is more severe than that, but why not allow ביטול?
bitul? It's all hamburger meat! Why not allow ביטול? bitul? Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara isn't answering that, it's just saying this is more
severe because we're dealing with a biblical problem. Well that's the reason
why. What? Yeah, but ביטול bitul works by biblical problems all the
time, right, you get a little חזיר chazir mixed up and so
on. Wait, let's just read the end, the end of this thought,
okay? דמר אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב אידי רישא בטומאת משקין דרבנן
סיפא דאורייתא. demar amar Rav Yitzchak brei d'Rav Idi reisha b'tumass mashkin
derabbanan seifa de'oraisa. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אבל בטומאת
שרץ מאי? aval b'tumass sheretz mai? So if the רישא reisha was
talking that it was טמא tamei because it touched actually a dead
rodent, right, it was biblical, what would you say? מאי? mai? לא
בטיל? lo batil?
Would it be בטל? batel?
אדתני סיפא והדר חתיכה של חטאת טהורה שנתערבה בטמאה חתיכה של חולין
טהורה לא תעלה.
aditni seifa v'hadar
chaticha shel
chatas tehora shenisarva b'tmeia chaticha shel chulin tehora lo sa'aleh. So when
you run to the second case to say if it's all טהור
tahor but חטאת chatas was חולין, chulin, it's not בטל, batel, נפלוג
וליתני בדידה. niflog v'lisni bdida. Why not make a distinction even by
the case of טומאה? tumah? Sometimes it's not בטל. batel. במה דברים
אמורים בטומאת משקין. bameh devarim amurim b'tumass mashkin. When is it not
בטל? batel? When it's a דרבנן טומאה derabbanan tumah and it's only
a דרבנן derabbanan problem. אבל בטומאת שרץ, aval b'tumass sheretz, if it's
a biblical טומאה, tumah, לא. lo. So it's not בטל. batel. Meaning
why do you have to run to a completely different case? Just
turn the case of טומאה tumah into a biblical טומאה tumah and
say it's not בטל. batel. So the גמרא Gemara gives the same
answer it gave before: טהורה בטהורה עדיף ליה. tehora b'tehora adif leih.
No, it rather would give you a scenario that everything is טהור
tahor and even though everything is טהור tahor and you might think
it's easier, even in that case it's not בטל. batel. So basically
the difference is according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, same point, this
is a דרבנן derabbanan problem, this is a דאורייתא de'oraisa problem. We
could have given you a דאורייתא de'oraisa problem here, but we wanted
to give you this scenario. One more answer about this: רבא אמר
רישא איסור לאו סיפא איסור כרת. Rava amar reisha issur lav seifa
issur kareis. רבא Rava says you don't have to go to... Negative
prohibition. But if you are a non כהן kohen eating חטאת chatas
טהורה, tehorah, or you're even a כהן kohen but you're טמא, tamei,
when you're טמא tamei and the קודש kodesh is טהור, tahor, that's
an איסור כרת. issur kares. When the קודש kodesh itself becomes טמא,
tamei, it itself gets defiled, so the level of severity lessens, goes
down. So this is only an איסור לאו. issur lav. Here it's
טהור tahor and you're a non כהן kohen. or you're טמא, tamei,
that's an איסור כרת. issur kares. So here ביטול bittul will work,
here ביטול bittul won't work because you're dealing with they're both biblical
but this is a much more severe איסור. issur. Okay, רבה, Rabba,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבה אמר רישא איסור לאו
סיפא איסור כרת. Rabba amar reisha issur lav seifa issur kares. והא
רבה הוא דאמר, ve-ha Rabba hu de-amar, one minute, רבה Rabba himself
says כל דאורייתא לא שני איסור לאו לא שני איסור כרת. kol
de-oraisa lo shnei issur lav lo shnei issur kares. רבה Rabba says
in another context that when you're dealing with a biblical prohibition and
issues of ביטול, bittul, we don't give any more weight to something
that's כרת kares as opposed to something that's a לאו, lav, meaning
we know we might give more weight to biblical over rabbinic, but
in a different discussion רבה Rabba said we give no more weight
to an איסור כרת issur kares over an איסור לאו, issur lav,
so how can we use that to explain this? קשיא, Kashya, that's
difficult. We'll give one last answer. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
and then we'll finish with this, סיפא משום דהוה ליה דבר שיש
לו מתירין וכל דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו באלף לא בטל. seifa
mishum de-hava lei davar she-yesh lo matirin ve-chol davar she-yesh lo matirin
afilu b-elef lo batel. At least he says that it's not just
more severe because we still haven't answered the question why shouldn't it
be בטל? batel? Let it be severe.
So רב אשי Rav Ashi says here's why it's not בטל.
batel. This is a דבר שיש לו מתירין davar she-yesh lo matirin
means there's a היתר. heter. What does דבר שיש לו מתירין davar
she-yesh lo matirin mean? It normally means you don't have to rely
on ביטול bittul because you can just wait and it'll be מותר.
muttar. Right? How will it wait and become מותר? muttar? So let's
say it's something like an egg that was born on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, נולד, nolad, got mixed up with other eggs. So you
don't, so we say oh well it's בטל. batel. He says no,
you don't have to say בטל. batel. Wait till tomorrow, it won't
be יום טוב, Yom Tov, you'll eat it tomorrow. So that's an
idea of we don't want to use ביטול bittul if you can
solve the problem by just waiting. Okay, so רב אשי Rav Ashi
says this you can't solve. If this is טמא tamei and not
בטל, batel, it's all אסור, assur, you got to throw it all
out. He says this you don't need ביטול. bittul. Why do you
not need ביטול? bittul? You can do it by היתר. heter. How
do you do it by היתר? heter? Not by waiting, but you
do it by היתר heter by just give it to a כהן.
kohen, So he says that's like a דבר שיש לו מתירין. davar
she-yesh lo matirin. The same way you could say wait till tomorrow
and you could eat it, רב אשי Rav Ashi says give it
to a כהן, kohen let the כהן kohen. eat it. And therefore
since there's a היתר heter way of eating it, we're not going
to allow ביטול. bittul. So that at least gives you a mechanism.
Until now we've just been saying this is more weighty. Who cares
that it's more weighty? ביטול bittul should still work by weighty things.
So רב אשי Rav Ashi says it's not because it's more weighty,
this is because there's a היתר heter way of doing it, just
give it to a כהן. kohen, Okay, so that's what he says.
דבר שיש לו מתירין אין בטל וכל דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו
באלף לא בטל.
davar she-yesh lo matirin ein batel ve-chol davar she-yesh lo matirin afilu
b-elef
lo batel. And now the גמרא Gemara ends, הדר רב אשי בדותיה.
hadar Rav Ashi bidusay. That was what רב אשי Rav Ashi said
is a joke. Okay, which means like it's, you know, it's absurd.
It's not true. He's got it totally wrong. Because this is not
דבר שיש לו מתירין. davar she-yesh lo matirin. למאן? le-man? Who is
this stuff permissible to? אי כהן, I kohen, if it's for a
כהן, kohen, מי שרי, mi-sharei, it was never אסור. assur. It was
always permitted. אי ישראל, I Yisrael, לעולם אסור. le-olam assur. For a
ישראל, Yisrael, it's always אסור. assur. אלא הדר רב אשי בדותיה. ela
hadar Rav Ashi bidusay. What רב אשי Rav Ashi says is foolishness,
which means like this: דבר שיש לו מתירין davar she-yesh lo matirin
is there's something here that's אסור. assur. The egg born on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. And therefore because it's אסור assur you want ביטול
bittul to work. But we're saying don't have ביטול bittul work, just
wait till tomorrow and it'll automatically become מותר. muttar. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying that's not what's going on here. If you're ישראל,
Yisrael, it was always אסור assur and it will always be אסור,
assur, the חטאת. chatas. If you're a כהן, kohen it was מותר
muttar and it will always be מותר. muttar. So it's not something
that was אסור assur and will become מותר. muttar. So this does
not fit in the דבר שיש לו מתירין davar she-yesh lo matirin
category. Yes, a כהן kohen can eat it, but that wouldn't allow
ביטול. bittul. I'm a ישראל, Yisrael, I want to eat it. Okay,
and it's never going to be מותר muttar for me. So why
should you say, you know, it's דבר שיש לו מתירין? davar she-yesh
lo matirin? So what we basically have is that according to ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, here it's muttar, here it's assur, it's all hamburger
meat, not clear why we're more strict here. We have three answers.
Number one is it's biblical, this is rabbinic. Number two, it's an
איסור כרת, issur kares, that's an איסור לאו. issur lav. And number
three is a כהן can eat it, but the גמרא said that's
absurd, that shouldn't be relevant. You're ישראל, Yisrael, you want to eat
it, that doesn't explain it. Again, what we don't know is big
deal that it's כרת kares or a לאו lav or דאורייתא, de-oraisa,
normally ביטול bittul should work. So we still don't understand why in
this ברייתא braisa ביטול bittul is not working, but anyway that's what
we're left with and we're left with the debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש Reish Lakish what the status of an אנדרוגינוס
androgynus is, we're left with a debate about whether תרומה terumah nowadays
is biblical or rabbinic, and we're left with a debate about whether
ביטול bittul works right when ביטול bittul doesn't work is it in
the narrow case of things that are exclusively counted, which is what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, or the broader case in things that
are sometimes counted, which is what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says. Yes,
Charlie? The issue of rabbinic תרומה terumah by liquids... The issue of
rabbinic תרומה Terumah by liquids, is that really true? There's a question
there about the status of liquids for תרומה. Terumah. But let's look
further. Look at the very top of דף ע''ג עמוד א'. Daf
Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph. וחכמים אומרים. V'Chachamim Omrim. וחכמים אומרים V'Chachamim Omrim
את שדרכו להימנות. Et shedarcho l'himanot. Things that are typically counted, they
are important, so they are not בטל. Batel.